so wondering if you could say something
about the
Sut if you had anything to say
about it's about PTI Sam just a short
verse mhm samayah
1241 it says uh and which is the noble
method which is properly seen by him the
noble disciple proper properly
penetrated with
understanding here householder Noble
disciple attends property from the
origin to this very dependent
origination when there is this there is
this when there isn't this there isn't
this when this arises this arises when
this ceases this
ceases that's that Noble method Noble
method is Noble understanding
Noble discernment so as the would have said
discernment so as the would have said
what what me what method is there it's
the one where he properly attends so you
can't do
bati you can either see it or not see it
and usually ptit is translated as
dependent origination and I suppose it's
a translation that's fine but the
problem is it um it carries on a view of
um of an explanatory
nature so it's like cause and effect
that's how people regard ptits oh this
is the cause this is the result this is
the new cause this is the new result but
it isn't the way the Buddha described it
it's a principle whereby while this is
present this is also the result of it so
it's a simultaneous presence so with the
presence of feeling there is presence of
craving in regard to that present
feeling it's not your craving is the
result of your
feeling they're simultaneously present
to the same extent not knowing how to
attend that not seeing a necessary
condition that presently endures within
your enduring craving that's how you
crave so a it's not an explanation of
what happens to you it's it's a it's a
direct Insight of how to appro things
that happen to you liability to craving
greed diversion delusion all these
things so that's why it's a noble method
method of overcoming
suffering but that's what we said how do
you do it you Noble disciple means you
need to have a Right View and you do it
by properly attending so you caught up
in craving you catch yourself full of
desire for whatever sense experience or
desire to get rid of
something what is the necessary basis
for that
desire can you have desire without
having craving can you oh I desire such and
craving can you oh I desire such and
such things without craving those things
can you have that it's
impossible so then any form of Desire
doesn't matter the specifics of your
desire requires presently enduring
craving attitude of
craving and you can stop there now you
can say okay so my desire is Root in my
craving you're not you're not you're not
basically overcoming it you might have
acknowledged it which is a good first
step but that's that won't overcome it
so then the Buddha said you attend
further what is another necessary basis
within craving necessary basis for
craving necessary basis for
craving exactly so you must be feeling
either Pleasant must be feeling either
unpleasant or must be feeling either
neither Pleasant or
unpleasant so you started with I want
this so much that you know I'm about to
do un wholesome things just to get it
you don't do it you practice sense
restraint but the desire is still there
through that desire you discern the
necessity of presently enduring craving
which is basically the container of that
desire now through that presently
enduring craving you discern a necessary
basis of presently enduring feeling
which is a container for your
craving and then you start dwelling
attending properly to the nature of that
Thon feeling have you created
it no did you have say it no you're
subjected to it so it's not yours even
if you want to make it yours you're only
basically maintaining it is yours
through not seeing it that it isn't
yours and through giving in habitually
towards the desire that's already
contained within the attitude of
craving so through giving into the
desire you maintain ignoring the nature
of the feeling which is that it can't be
yours because if you stop ignoring it
you see that it can't be yours craving
disappears and disappears by being included within
and disappears by being included within
the Oris feeling not by you choosing to
like pick it and remove it so then when
the craving
disappears are you talking about the
right that's right view then well all of
this like if if somebody has the right
view already all of this would be just
uh further development of that right
view uh but even if you don't have the
right view training yourself how to
discern craving within the desire how to
discern feeling within craving not
before or after not as as result
psychologization or explanation oh I
crave because I have no while you crave
you discern presently during feeling so
while you crave you feel and it's the
craving in regard to feeling you cannot
have craving second longer if the
feeling disappears but you can have
feeling well you can have feeling
without craving but the only way to
understand that is through abandoning
the craving not like finding out how to
not crave on top of your craving so the
only way to abandon to to understand how
you can have feeling without craving is
to first through craving you discern the
necessary basis of feeling and then
abandon craving by by fully
understanding that necessary basis
that's exactly PTI po nothing else with
this as a necessary basis this is
enduring engaging me making me act
making me feel all of these
things so that's why there's so many
different uh variations of ptit the
sutas 16 factors 12 factors eight
factors Sometimes some were methed some
included some added because they are the
principle principle of Discerning the
necessary basis for another
simultaneously enduring phenomena it's
not an explanation it's not a it's not a
it's not like a linear sort of set of
visualizations you have to go through in
order to practice it none of that
Discerning what is my present situation
is there a sense desire in me no is
there absence of sense desire in me yes
what is the present feeling on account
of
that is there any desire towards that
feeling so now I have a peaceful feeling
neutral feeling do I have desire to to
sort of want that feeling
more in which case well it's not anym
neutral it's unpleasant
now and and in regard to the body seeing
the body and and external yeah external
objects can you can you even can you
even can you even fathom can you even
think imagine in utter complete
abstraction any external object without
the necessary basis of your
body impossible so seeing those two those two
impossible so seeing those two those two
well seeing basically the right Order of
Things seeing this within
this not this within
that and that's the difference in the in
P about like when not seen then yeah
your feelings are result of your craving
CU that's how you assume them
they're not but you don't know that
they're not and because of that the only
reality you know is the reality that
yeah you are craving and all this that's
why it's like a vicious circle until you
understand that your craving cannot make
a difference to the nature of being
subjected to the feeling and that your
craving can never step outside of the
feeling it requires feeling as a
necessary container for it to endure for
it to
manifest so you don't want to be doing
reflecting upon PTI like on random
things CU it's already subtle enough to
be
understood she going to just make it
more abstract you want to find practical
side of it practical is feeling freedom
from it as in Freedom from craving in
regard to it which is freedom from
suffering because one who sees the D
sees one who sees sees the D
so literally the entire Dharma is in
that principle and why is it that why is
that principle so important so profound
because if you see that your presently
enduring desire fully embedded in the
attitude of your craving for this
craving for this to not be craving for
this to be uh if you see all of that
that experience in its entirety is fully
contained fully determined formed the
Sankara by the presently enduring
feeling that you've been subjected to
you haven't created it you realize the
utmost of your desires and cravings and
wills it's actually rooted in something
else not you and thus cannot be yours
even if you engage with
it but by not dwelling on that long
enough you do develop the notion of I am
my own uh my own like my own possessions
my own feelings my own C my own desires
and everything else is the result of
that but it's out way around so you want to
but it's out way around so you want to
start including it in a bigger
context context that yeah your mind must
be like might be feverish with the
desire for this particular object
peripheral to that is the necessity of
the attitude of craving can you have
desire without craving for what you
desire no so you realize okay so whenever there
no so you realize okay so whenever there
is a desire I know craving is there I
don't need to see it written on the
craving no I know this desire is present
means craving is here desire is a
symptom of the attitude of
craving once you become familiar with
that you take it step further but the
same same principle and that's what you
learn how to attend properly so instead
of attending it what craving is pushing
you towards you attended the necessary
basis for the push of the craving that y
you attend to the boom to the back to
the origin of this attitude that I have
that I'm not denying but I'm not
engaging with it either that's why
sensory strain comes first then you get
to understand and then you just get to
be drilling and drilling the same
understanding through same way of
properly attending and that's the noble
method that's the noble method
exactly as concise as you can explain it